<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter id="execution">
   <title>Test execution</title>

   <para>
      This chapter walks through the details of test execution, covering both the remote and local container cases.
   </para>
   
   <note>
      <para>
         Whilst it's not necessary to understand the details of how Arquillian works, it is often useful to have some
         insight. This chapter gives you an overview of how Arquillian executes your test for you in your chosen
         container.  
      </para>
   </note>

   <section>
      <title>Anatomy of a test</title>

      <para>
         In both JUnit 4 and TestNG 5, a test case is a class which contains at least one test method. The test method
         is designated using the <literal>@Test</literal> annotation from the respective framework. An Arquillian test
         case looks just like a regular JUnit or TestNG test case with two declarative enhancements:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>The class contains a static method annotated with <literal>@Deployment</literal> that returns a <literal>JavaArchive</literal></para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               The class is annotated with <literal>@RunWith(Arquillian.class)</literal> (JUnit) or extends
               <literal>Arquillian</literal> (TestNG)
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         With those two modifications in place, the test is recognized by the Arquillian test runner and will be
         executed in the target container. It can also use the extra functionality that Arquillian provides&#8212;namely
         container resource injections and the injection of beans.
      </para>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>ShrinkWrap packaging</title>
   
      <para>
         When the Arquillian test runner processes a test class, the first thing it does is retrieve the definition of
         the Java archive from the <literal>@Deployment</literal> method, appends the test class to the archive and
         packages the archive using ShrinkWrap.
      </para>

      <para>
         The name of the archive is irrelevant, so the base name "test" is typically choosen (e.g., test.jar, test.war).
         Once you have created the shell of the archive, the sky is really the limit of how you can assemble it. You are
         customizing the layout and contents of the archive to suit the needs of the test. Essentially, you creating a
         micro application in which to execute the code under test.
      </para>

      <para>
         You can add the following artifacts to the test archive:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Java classes</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>A Java package (which adds all the Java classes in the package)</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Classpath resources</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>File system resources</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>A programmatically-defined file</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Java libraries (JAR files)</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Other Java archives defined by ShrinkWrap</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         Consult the <ulink url="http://docs.jboss.org/shrinkwrap/1.0.0-alpha-11/">ShrinkWrap API</ulink> to discover all the options you have available for constructing the test archive.
      </para>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Test archive deployment</title>

      <para>
         After the Arquillian test runner packages the test archive, it deploys it to the container. For a remote
         container, this means copying the archive the hot deployment directory or deploying the archive using the
         container's remote deployment service. In the case of a local container, such as Weld SE, deploying the archive
         simply means registering the contents of the archive with the runtime environment.
      </para>

      <para>
         <emphasis>How does Arquillian support multiple containers? And how are both remote and local cases
         supported?</emphasis> The answer to this question gets into the extensibility of Arquillian.
      </para>

      <para>
         Arquillian delegates to an SPI (service provider interface) to handle starting and stopping the server and
         deploying and undeploying archives. In this case, the SPI is the interface
         <literal>org.jboss.arquillian.spi.client.DeployableContainer</literal>. If you recall from the getting started
         section, we included an Arquillian library according to the target container we wanted to use. That library
         contains an implementation of this interface, thus controlling how Arquillian handles deployment. If you wanted to
         introduce support for another container in Arquillian, you would simply provide an implementation of this
         interface.
      </para>

      <para>
         With the archive deployed, all is left is negotiating execution of the test and capturing the results. As you
         would expect, once all the methods in the test class have be run, the archive is undeployed.
      </para>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Enriching the test class</title>

      <para>
         The last operation that Arquillian performs before executing the individual test methods is "enriching" the
         test class instance. This means hooking the test class to the container environment by satisfying its injection
         points. The enrichment is provided by any implementation of the
         <literal>org.jboss.arquillian.spi.TestEnricher</literal> SPI on the classpath. <xref linkend="enrichment"/>
         details the injection points that Arquillian supports.
      </para>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Negotiating test execution</title>

      <para>
         The question at this point is, how does Arquillian negotiate with the container to execute the test
         when the test framework is being invoked locally? Technially the mechanism is pluggable using another SPI,
         <literal>org.jboss.arquillian.spi.ContainerMethodExecutor</literal>. Arquillian provides a default
         implementation for remote servers which uses HTTP communication and an implementation for local tests, which
         works through direct execution of the test in the same JVM. Let's have a look at how the remote execution
         works.
      </para>

      <para>
         The archive generator bundles and registers (in the web.xml descriptor) an HttpServlet,
         org.jboss.arquillian.protocol.servlet.ServletTestRunner, that responds to test execution GET requests. The test
         runner on the client side delegates to the <literal>org.jboss.arquillian.spi.ContainerMethodExecutor</literal>
         SPI implementation, which originates these test execution requests to transfer control to the container JVM.
         The name of the test class and the method to be executed are specified in the request query parameters named
         className and methodName, respectively.
      </para>

      <para>
         When the test execution request is received, the servlet delegates to an implementation of the
         <literal>org.jboss.arquillian.spi.TestRunner</literal> SPI, passing it the name of the test class and the test
         method.  <literal>TestRunner</literal> generates a test suite dynamically from the test class and method name
         and runs the suite (now within the context of the container).
      </para>

      <para>
         The <literal>ServletTestRunner</literal> translates the native test result object of JUnit or TestNG into a
         <literal>org.jboss.arquillian.spi.TestResult</literal> and passes it back to the test executor on the client
         side by serializing the translated object into the response. The object gets encoded as either html or a
         serialized object, depending on the value of the outputMode request parameter that was passed to the servlet.
         Once the result has been transfered to the client-side test runner, the testing framework (JUnit or TestNG)
         wraps up the run of the test as though it had been executed in the same JVM.
     </para>

     <para>
        Now you should have an understanding for how tests can be executed inside the container, but still be executed
        using existing IDE, Ant and Maven test plugins without any modification. Perhaps you have even started thinking
        about ways in which you can enhance or extend Arquillian. But there's still one challenge that remains for
        developing tests with Arquillian. How do you debug test? We'll look at how to hook a debugger into the test
        execution process in the next chapter.
     </para>

<!--
There's one piece missing. How does TestNG on the client side know to submit a request to the
ServletTestRunner servlet to get TestNG to execute the test in the container JVM? That's the
role of the test launcher.

The test launcher is the API that allows test suite to launch the test in a pluggable fashion.
AbstractTest, the super class of AbtractJSR299Test, implements IHookable, a TestNG
interface which allows the execution of the test method to be intercepted. Using that mechanism,
AbstractTest delegates execution of the test method (a method annotated with @Test in
an @Artifact class) to an implementation of org.jboss.testharness.api.TestLauncher
if the tests are being executed in-container. As you might anticipate, the implementation is
specified using a property with the same name as the interface in a META-INF/jboss-test-
launcher.properties resource. The JBoss Test Harness provides a default implementation,
org.jboss.testharness.impl.runner.servlet.ServletTestLauncher, that hooks into the
HTTP communication infrastructure described above. It invokes the ServletTestRunner servlet
for each method annotated with @Test in the @Artifact that is not otherwise disabled.
-->

   </section>

	<section>
		<title>Test run modes</title>
		
		<para>
			So far, we've focused on testing your application internals, but we also want to test how others (people, or other programs) 
			interact with the application. Typically, you want to make sure that every use case and execution path is fully tested. 
			Third parties can interact with your application in a number of ways, for example web services, remote EJBs or via http. 
			You need to check that you object serialization or networking work for instance. 
		</para>
		<para>			
			This is why Arquillian comes with two run modes, <literal>in container</literal> and <literal>as client</literal>.
			<literal>in container</literal> is to test your application internals and <literal>as client</literal> is to test 
			how your application is used by clients. Lets dive a bit deeper into the differences between the run modes and 
			see how they effect your test execution and packaging.			
		</para>

		<section>
			<title>Mode: in-container</title>
			<programlisting role="JAVA">@Deployment(testable = true)</programlisting>			
			<para>
				As we mentioned above, we need to repackage your <literal>@Deployment</literal>, adding some Arquillian support 
				classes, to run in-container. This gives us the ability to communicate with the test, enrich the test and run the 
				test remotely. In this mode, the test executes in the remote container; Arqullian uses this mode by default.
			</para>

			<para>
				See the <link linkend="protocol.reference">Complete Protocol Reference</link> for an overview of the expected output of the packaging process when you provide a <literal>@Deployment</literal>.			
			</para>			
		</section>		

		<section>
			<title>Mode: as-client</title>
			<programlisting role="JAVA">@Deployment(testable = false)</programlisting>			
			<para>
				Now this mode is the easy part. As apposed to in-container mode which repackages and overrides the test 
				execution, the as-client mode does as little as possible. It does not repackage your <literal>@Deployment</literal>
				nor does it forward the test execution to a remote server. Your test case is running in your JVM as expected
				and you're free to test the container from the outside, as your clients see it. The only thing Arquillian 
				does is to control the lifecycle of your <literal>@Deployment</literal>.  
			</para>

			<para>Here is an example calling a Servlet using the <literal>as client</literal> mode.</para>
			<programlisting role="JAVA">@RunWith(Arquillian.class)
public class LocalRunServletTestCase
{
   @Deployment(testable = false)
   public static WebArchive createDeployment() 
   {
      return ShrinkWrap.create("test.war", WebArchive.class)
               .addClass(TestServlet.class);
   }
   
   @Test
   public void shouldBeAbleToCallServlet(@ArquillianResource(TestServlet.class) URL baseUrl) throws Exception
   {
   	  // http://localhost:8080/test/
      String body = readAllAndClose(new URL(baseUrl, "/Test").openStream());
      
      Assert.assertEquals(
            "Verify that the servlet was deployed and returns the expected result",
            "hello",
            body);
   }
}</programlisting>
		</section>		

		<section>
			<title>Mode: mixed</title>
			<programlisting role="JAVA">@Deployment(testable = true)
public static WebArchive create() 
{
}

@Test // runs in container
public void shouldBeAbleToRunOnClientSide() throws Exception 
{
}

@Test @RunAsClient // runs as client
public void shouldBeAbleToRunOnClientSide() throws Exception 
{
}</programlisting>
			<para>
				It is also possible to mix the two run modes within the same test class. If you have defined the <literal>Deployment</literal>
				to be testable, you can specify the <literal>@Test</literal> method to use run mode <literal>as client</literal> by using 
				the <literal>@RunAsClient</literal> annotation. This will allow two method	within the same test class to run in different modes. 
				This can be useful if you in a run <literal>as client</literal> mode want to execute against a remote endpoint in your application, 
				for then in the next test method assert on server side state the remote endpoint migh thave created.
			</para>
		</section>		

		<tip>
			<para>
				The effect of the different run modes depend on the <literal>DeployableContainer</literal> used. 
				Both modes might seem to behave the same in some Embedded containers, but you should avoid
				mixing your internal and external tests. One thing is that they should test different
				aspects of your application and different usecases, another is that you will miss the 
				benefits of switching <literal>DeployableContainers</literal> and run the same tests suite against
				a remote server if you do.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</section>

<!--
vim:et:ts=3:sw=3:tw=120
-->
</chapter>
