<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter id="gettingstarted">

   <title>Getting started</title>

   <para>
      We've promised you that integration testing with Arquillian is no more complicated than writing a unit test. Now
      it's time to prove it to you.  In this chapter, we'll look at what is required to setup Arquillian in your
      project, how to write an Arquillian test case, how to execute the test case and how the test results are
      displayed. That sounds like a lot, but you'll be writing your own Arquillian tests in no time. (You'll also learn
      about <xref linkend="debugging"/> in Chapter 7).
   </para>

   <section>
      <title>Setting up Arquillian in a Maven project</title>
      
      <para>
         The quickest way to get started with Arquillian is to add it to an existing Maven 2 project. Regardless of
         whether you plan to use Maven as your project build, we recommend that you take your first steps with
         Arquillian this way so as to get to your first green bar with the least amount of distraction.
      </para>

      <para>
         The first thing you should do is define a Maven property for the version of Arquillian you are going to use.
         This way, you only have to maintain the version in one place and can reference it using the Maven variable
         syntax everywhere else in your build file.
      </para>

      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<properties>
   <arquillian.version>1.0.0.Alpha5</arquillian.version>
</properties>]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         Make sure you have the correct APIs available for your test. In this test we are going to use CDI:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency> 
   <groupId>javax.enterprise</groupId> 
   <artifactId>cdi-api</artifactId> 
   <version>1.0-SP1</version>  
</dependency>]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         Next, you'll need to decide whether you are going to write tests in JUnit 4.x or TestNG 5.x. Once you make that
         decision (use TestNG if you're not sure), you'll need to add either the JUnit or TestNG library to your test
         build path as well as the corresponding Arquillian library.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         If you plan to use <emphasis>JUnit 4</emphasis>, begin by adding the following two test-scoped dependencies to
         the <literal>&lt;dependencies&gt;</literal> section of your pom.xml.
      </para>

      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency> 
   <groupId>junit</groupId> 
   <artifactId>junit</artifactId> 
   <version>4.8.1</version> 
   <scope>test</scope> 
</dependency> 

<dependency>
   <groupId>org.jboss.arquillian</groupId>
   <artifactId>arquillian-junit</artifactId>
   <version>${arquillian.version}</version>
   <scope>test</scope>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         If you plan to use <emphasis>TestNG</emphasis>, then add these two test-scoped dependencies instead:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency> 
   <groupId>org.testng</groupId> 
   <artifactId>testng</artifactId> 
   <version>5.12.1</version> 
   <scope>test</scope> 
</dependency> 

<dependency>
   <groupId>org.jboss.arquillian</groupId>
   <artifactId>arquillian-testng</artifactId>
   <version>${arquillian.version}</version>
   <scope>test</scope>
</dependency>
]]></programlisting>

     <para>
        That covers the libraries you need to write your first Arquillian test case. We'll revisit the pom.xml file in a
        moment to add the library you need to execute the test.
     </para>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Writing your first Arquillian test</title>

      <para>
         You're now going to write your first Arquillian test. But in order to write a test, we need to have something
         to test. So let's first create a managed bean that we can invoke.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         We'll help out those Americans still trying to convert to the metric system by providing them a Fahrenheit to
         Celsius converter.
      </para>

      <para>
         Here's our <literal>TemperatureConverter</literal>:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class TemperatureConverter {

   public double convertToCelsius(double f) {
      return ((f - 32) * 5 / 9);
   }

   public double convertToFarenheit(double c) {
      return ((c * 9 / 5) + 32);
   }

}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         Now we need to validate that this code runs. We'll be creating a test in the <literal>src/test/java</literal>
         classpath of the project.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         Granted, in this trivial case, we could simply instantiate the implementation class in a unit test to test the
         calculations. However, let's assume that this bean is more complex, needing to access enterprise services. We
         want to test it as a full-blown container-managed bean, not just as a simple class instance. Therefore,
         we'll inject the bean into the test class using the <literal>@Inject</literal> annotation.
      </para>

      <para>
         You're probably very familiar with writing tests using either JUnit or TestNG. A regular JUnit or TestNG test
         class requires two enhancements to make it an Arquillian integration test:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Define the deployment archive for the test using ShrinkWrap</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Declare for the test to use the Arquillian test runner</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         The deployment archive for the test is defined using a static method annotated with Arquillian's
         <literal>@Deployment</literal> annotation that has the following signature: 
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public static Archive<?> methodName();]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         We'll add the managed bean to the archive so that we have something to test. We'll also add an 
         empty <literal>beans.xml</literal> file, so that the deployment is CDI-enabled:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Deployment
public static JavaArchive createTestArchive() {
   return ShrinkWrap.create(JavaArchive.class, "test.jar")
      .addClasses(TemperatureConverter.class)
      .addAsManifestResource(
            new ByteArrayAsset("<beans/>".getBytes()), 
            ArchivePaths.create("beans.xml"));
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         The JUnit and TestNG versions of our test class will be nearly identical. They will only differ in how they
         hook into the Arquillian test runner.
      </para>

      <para>
         When creating the JUnit version of the Arquillian test case, you will define at least one test method annotated
         with the JUnit <literal>@Test</literal> annotation and also annotate the class with the
         <literal>@RunWith</literal> annotation to indicate that Arquillian should be used as the test runner for this
         class.
      </para>

      <para>
         Here's the JUnit version of our test class:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@RunWith(Arquillian.class)
public class TemperatureConverterTest {
   @Inject
   private TemperatureConverter converter;

   @Deployment
   public static JavaArchive createTestArchive() {
      return ShrinkWrap.create(JavaArchive.class, "test.jar")
         .addClasses(TemperatureConverter.class)
         .addAsManifestResource(
            EmptyAsset.INSTANCE, 
            ArchivePaths.create("beans.xml")); 
   }

   @Test
   public void testConvertToCelsius() {
      Assert.assertEquals(converter.convertToCelsius(32d), 0d);
      Assert.assertEquals(converter.convertToCelsius(212d), 100d);
   }

   @Test
   public void testConvertToFarenheit() {
      Assert.assertEquals(converter.convertToFarenheit(0d), 32d);
      Assert.assertEquals(converter.convertToFarenheit(100d), 212d);
   }
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         TestNG doesn't provide anything like JUnit's <literal>@RunWith</literal> annotation, so instead the TestNG
         version of the Arquillian test case must extend the Arquillian class and define at least one method annotated
         with TestNG's <literal>@Test</literal> annotation.
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class TemperatureConverterTest extends Arquillian {
   @Inject
   private TemperatureConverter converter;

   @Deployment
   public static JavaArchive createTestArchive() {
      return ShrinkWrap.create(JavaArchive.class, "test.jar")
         .addClasses(TemperatureConverter.class)
         .addAsManifestResource(
            EmptyAsset.INSTANCE,, 
            ArchivePaths.create("beans.xml")); 
   }

   @Test
   public void testConvertToCelsius() {
      Assert.assertEquals(converter.convertToCelsius(32d), 0d);
      Assert.assertEquals(converter.convertToCelsius(212d), 100d);
   }

   @Test
   public void testConvertToFarenheit() {
      Assert.assertEquals(converter.convertToFarenheit(0d), 32d);
      Assert.assertEquals(converter.convertToFarenheit(100d), 212d);
   }
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         As you can see, we are not instantiating the bean implementation class directly, but rather using the CDI
         reference provided by the container at the injection point, just as it would be used in the application. (If
         the target container supports EJB, you could replace the <literal>@Inject</literal> annotation with
         <literal>@EJB</literal>). Now let's
         see if this baby passes!
      </para>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Setting up and running the test in Maven</title>

      <para>
         As we've been emphasizing, this test is going to run inside of a container. That means you have to have a
         container running somewhere. While you can execute tests in an embedded container or a Java SE CDI environment,
         we're going to start off by testing using the real deal.
      </para>

      <para>
         If you haven't already, download the latest version of JBoss AS 6.0 from the <ulink
         url="http://www.jboss.org/jbossas/downloads/">JBoss AS download page</ulink>, extract the distribution and
         start the container.
      </para>

      <para>
         Since Arquillian needs to perform JNDI lookups to get references to the components under test, we need to
         include a <literal>jndi.properties</literal> file on the test classpath. Create the file
         <literal>src/test/resources/jndi.properties</literal> and populate it with the following contents:
      </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[java.naming.factory.initial=org.jnp.interfaces.NamingContextFactory
java.naming.factory.url.pkgs=org.jboss.naming:org.jnp.interfaces 
java.naming.provider.url=jnp://localhost:1099]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         Next, we're going to return to pom.xml to add another dependency. Arquillian picks which container it's going
         to use to deploy the test archive and negotiate test execution using the service provider mechanism, meaning
         which implementation of the <literal>DeployableContainer</literal> SPI is on the classpath. We'll control
         that through the use of Maven profiles. Add the following profiles to pom.xml:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<profiles>
   <profile>
      <id>jbossas-remote-6</id>
      <dependencies>
         <dependency>
            <groupId>org.jboss.arquillian.container</groupId>
            <artifactId>arquillian-jbossas-remote-6</artifactId>
            <version>${arquillian.version}</version>
         </dependency>
		<dependency>
			<groupId>org.jboss.jbossas</groupId>
			<artifactId>jboss-as-client</artifactId>
			<version>6.0.0.Final</version>
			<type>pom</type>
		</dependency>
      </dependencies>
   </profile>
</profiles>]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         You would setup a similar profile for each Arquillian-supported container in which you want your tests
         executed. <!-- reference to containers chapter for details -->
      </para>

      <para>
         All that's left is to execute the tests. In Maven, that's easy. Simply run the Maven test goal with the
         <literal>jbossas-remote-6</literal> profile activated:
      </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[mvn test -Pjbossas-remote-6]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        You should see that the two tests pass.
      </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[-------------------------------------------------------
 T E S T S
-------------------------------------------------------
Running TemperatureConverterTest
Tests run: 2, Failures: 0, Errors: 0, Skipped: 0, Time elapsed: 1.964 sec

Results :

Tests run: 2, Failures: 0, Errors: 0, Skipped: 0

[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] BUILD SUCCESSFUL
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         The tests are passing, but we don't see a green bar. To get that visual, we need to run the tests in the IDE.
         Arquillian tests can be executed using existing IDE plugins for JUnit and TestNG, respectively, or so you've
         been told. It's once again time to prove it.
      </para>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Setting up and running the test in Eclipse</title>

      <para>
         Before running an Arquillian test in Eclipse, you must have the plugin for the unit testing framework you are
         using installed. Eclipse ships with the JUnit plugin, so you are already setup if you selected JUnit.  If you
         are writing your tests with TestNG, you need the Eclipse <ulink url="http://testng.org">TestNG plugin</ulink>.
      </para>
      
      <note>
   </note>
      
      <para>
         Since the example in this guide is based on a Maven 2 project, you will also need the m2eclipse plugin. Instructions for
         using the m2eclipse update site to add the m2eclipse plugin to Eclipse are provided on the m2eclipse home page.
         For more, read the m2eclipse <ulink url="http://www.sonatype.com/books/m2eclipse-book/reference">reference
         guide</ulink>.
      </para>

      <para>
         Once the plugins are installed, import your Maven project into the Eclipse workspace. Before executing the
         test, you need to enable the profile for the target container, as you did in the previous section. We'll
         go ahead and activate the profile globally for the project. Right click on the project and select Properties.
         Select the Maven property sheet and in the first form field, enter <literal>jbossas-remote-6</literal>; you also need
         to tell Maven to not resolve depedencies from the workspace (this interferes with resource loading):
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="images/maven-properties-screen.png" format="PNG" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="images/maven-properties-screen.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
         </imageobject>
         <caption>
            <para>Maven settings for project</para>
         </caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>
         Click OK and accept the project changes. Before we execute tests, make sure that Eclipse has properly processed all
         the resource files by running a full build on the project by selecting Clean from Project menu. Now you are ready
         to execute tests.
      </para>

      <para>
         Right click on the TemperatureConverterTest.java file in the Package Explorer and select Run As... > JUnit Test
         or Run As... > TestNG Test depending on which unit testing framework the test is using.
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="images/junit-run-test.png" format="PNG" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="images/junit-run-test.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
         </imageobject>
         <caption>
            <para>Running the the JUnit test in Eclipse</para>
         </caption>
      </mediaobject>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Setting up and running the test in NetBeans</title>

      <para>
         Things get even simpler when using NetBeans 6.8 or better. NetBeans ships with native Maven 2 support and,
         rather than including a test plugin for each unit testing framework, it has a generic test plugin which
         delegates to the Maven surefire plugin to execute the tests.
      </para>

      <para>
         Import your Maven project into NetBeans. Then, look for a select menu in the main toolbar, which you can
         use to set the active Maven profile. Select the <literal>jbossas-remote-6</literal> profile as shown here:
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="images/netbeans-project-configuration.png" format="PNG" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="images/netbeans-project-configuration.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
         </imageobject>
         <caption>
            <para>NetBeans project configuration</para>
         </caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>
         Now you are ready to test. Simply right click on the TemperatureConverter.java file in the Projects pane and
         select Test File. NetBeans will delegate to the Maven surefire plugin to execute the tests and then
         display the results in a result windown, showing us a pretty green bar!
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="images/netbeans-green-bar.png" format="PNG" align="center" scale="75"/>
         </imageobject>
         <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="images/netbeans-green-bar.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
         </imageobject>
         <caption>
            <para>Successful test report in NetBeans</para>
         </caption>
      </mediaobject>

   </section>

   <para>
      As you can see, there was no special configuration necessary to execute the tests in either Eclipse or NetBeans.
   </para>

<!--
vim:et:ts=3:sw=3:tw=120
-->
</chapter>
